<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Harsha Sista</title>
    <link>https://atsis98.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://atsis98.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Harsha Sista</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 21:34:36 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://atsis98.github.io/images/icon_hu3f7b2b206f3b1a0e7569742943667eab_21402_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Harsha Sista</title>
      <link>https://atsis98.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Italian Job</title>
      <link>https://atsis98.github.io/post/milan-thesis-tales/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 21:34:36 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://atsis98.github.io/post/milan-thesis-tales/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My name is Harsha Sista, and I shall be your journalist/protagonist in this edition of Thesis Tales. As a final year Mechanical Engineering student at BPHC, I had to dedicate a semester to pursue either the Practice School II program or switch to a thesis. Cultivating an inclination towards the world of research through my second and third years of college, I decided that it would benefit my future if I pursued a thesis and got a taste of how life in academia would be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve had an affinity for outer space and flying objects since childhood, and I aimed to convert that into a tangible career path during my undergraduate studies. From taking up online and on-campus courses to further my understanding to being a part of various technical teams, I attempted to mould my profile to become proficient with fluid mechanics and dynamics. Hoping to work in Aerodynamics or Computational Fluid Dynamics, I started looking up about various professors at prestigious institutions across the globe who worked in these fields, going by their research interests and the corresponding research output. After creating a shortlist, I started sending out emails in January 2019, which was rather late in hindsight. I mailed around 170 professors, out of which I received around 30 rejections. Towards the end of February, I finally got an acceptance from Prof. Luigi Vigevano at the Department of Aerospace Engineering, Politecnico di Milano (Polimi). I was elated at the prospect of going to an institute ranked #7 by QS in Aerospace Engineering, and began the formalities of the PS to Thesis conversion and my Visa Application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never having been out of the country – going to Milan promised to be an eye-opening experience. In addition to hosting one of the premier research institutes in the world, Milan is also a cultural epicenter, which appealed to my interests. August is the summer month in Italy, during which most colleges have holidays. Polimi was scheduled to remain shut for an entire week, so I planned a short trip across the beautiful land of Italy at that time. Hopping from Rome to Venice, while visiting Florence, Pisa, and the coastal villages of Cinque Terre, the week-long trip provided memories for a lifetime. In addition, Milan houses the San Siro, the shared football stadium of AC Milan and Internazionale, and is also home to the Formula 1 track at Monza. Being an avid fan of both sports, I attended three Champions League matches and the 2019 Italian Grand Prix at Monza, fulfilling a lifelong dream of being present at a live sporting event. Even if you disregard these high-profile sporting attractions, Milan can be described as a crossroad where the classics and the modern meet. It is truly a wonderfully vibrant city, ensuring that my free time was well spent exploring the city on foot and through the immaculate public transportation system.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-attending-the-2019-italian-grand-prix-at-monza&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img src=&#34;f1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Attending the 2019 Italian Grand Prix at Monza
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked at Polimi from mid-July to the end of December, a duration of 5 and a half months. My work involved running simulations on their in-house software called ROSITA and investigating the aerodynamic and aeroacoustic features of rotating helicopter blades. I worked directly with Prof. Vigevano, with Jinbin Fu, a Ph.D. student, occasionally helping me out. Although I knew the principles of aerodynamics, aeroacoustics was a new field for me, and operating the Linux terminal to tweak the software and run simulations taught me a lot. It took a bit of time to get used to the new environment and the task expected of me, with most of July and August going in familiarizing myself with the software and the concepts required for me to run the simulations. Prof. Vigevano was immensely helpful in this process, and once I was confident enough, the simulations and analysis of results were familiar territories.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-the-rotorcraft-aerodynamic-laboratory&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;laboratory.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;750&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The Rotorcraft Aerodynamic Laboratory
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of funding, I could not receive any funding from BITS. After consultations with Prof. Vigevano, it was decided that I would not be required to pay any fee to Polimi, although there would be no funds to support my stay in Milan. While this seemed a costly endeavor, I believe it was worth every rupee, for the enormity of the opportunity and the plethora of avenues it opened for me.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-prof-vigevano-and-me&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;featured.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;500&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Prof. Vigevano and me
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people ask me about the benefit of doing an off-campus thesis abroad. I would say that it boils down to two parameters: international research exposure and an opportunity to make an informed decision about your future. The research environment is very different abroad, as compared to India. While our curriculum focuses on bookish learning with provisions to gain hands-on experience, learning among peers, and meaningful academic interactions with Professors are two things I feel are underrepresented in the Indian College Education system. While BITS follows a modern approach with a flexible curriculum and a competent peer group, I feel that the system is open enough to incorporate both of the above aspects to help us learn better. Apart from that, the facilities I found at Polimi were cutting-edge in most respects, providing a perfect base for academic research to take flight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding my point about making an informed decision, the thesis gave me a glimpse into my future, teaching me the appropriate research methodology and the avenues to be explored in academia. This experience converted my initial feeling of being confused between a master&amp;rsquo;s degree a Ph.D. into a clearer idea of pursuing a Ph.D. in the subfield of Aerodynamics. This process of gaining clarity is crucial in deciding your academic future, as a hasty decision at this juncture might lead to unfavorable consequences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, my time in Milan was fruitful and helped me learn a lot about research and myself. I would say it helped me grow as a person and gave me all the necessary tools to decide my academic future, for which I am thankful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I believe it can fly</title>
      <link>https://atsis98.github.io/post/airplane/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Aug 2020 19:57:52 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://atsis98.github.io/post/airplane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The miracle of flight has astounded humans for centuries. Since the dawn of time, there have been stories, myths, and legends talking about mankind&amp;rsquo;s attempt to mimic the flight of birds and make the skies his own. From the winged Pegasus overthrowing monsters on the battlefield to the tragic tale of Icarus - the man who flew too high, these stories perhaps reflect the failed attempts made by the ancients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we may not know much about the distant past, the journey to flight has had many key moments from the middle ages: Leonardo da Vinci&amp;rsquo;s schematics that were ahead of their time, the Montgolfier brothers taking to the skies aboard a hot air balloon and the various gliders that were designed by George Cayley and Otto Lilienthal. However, the moment that history has immortalized is the daring hop across 120 feet that the engine-powered contraption that the Wright brothers fabricated at Kitty Hawk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From that 1903 breakthrough, the concept of flight took off, reaching greater heights and capturing the public&amp;rsquo;s imagination. In a few short years, Lindbergh and Amelia Earhart&amp;rsquo;s trans-Atlantic flights, the development of military aircraft for the World Wars, and the development of aviation giants post-WW II have brought the impossible to the common man. You might be wondering why I am giving you a lesson in the history of flight; I am doing so to give an insight into why I am inspired by the phenomenon and how it came to be.
I&amp;rsquo;ve always been a voracious reader, ever since I learned how to, at a very young age. Although I loved stories, the books that fascinated me the most were the Young Scientist and Childcraft book series, which aimed to give kids an introduction to science and technology. I found myself drawn towards the books that talked about space exploration and the way humans defied the gravity of the Earth to quite literally reach for the stars.
As that childhood dream matured into adolescence, I started to think in terms of choosing a career that would have me working towards my passion, taking up a science stream in high school. I was in Class 11 when we had someone come and teach us how to make a plane with balsa wood as part of our school&#39; Cultural Week&amp;quot;. That was where I first got the opportunity to convert a dream into a tangible reality. We used the energy stored in a twisted rubber band to rotate the rudimentary propeller and had a competition to see whose plane would be the most stable and fly the farthest.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-the-balsa-plane-i-left-built-with-the-help-of-my-classmates&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/post/airplane/Balsa_hu601d16702d14b37cc2e74d2d7f41670a_102313_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;500&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The balsa plane I (left) built with the help of my classmates
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After graduating from school, I took up Mechanical Engineering as my undergraduate major at BITS Pilani, Hyderabad Campus, the top-ranked private university in India. I took part in various competitions and extracurricular activities, building my skill-set and learning as much as I could. In my fourth semester, we were required to design something for the Production Techniques course and spend the next semester fabricating it using some techniques taught in the course. By this time, I had learned the basics of flight theory from online courses and had an understanding of how an object heavier than air could fly.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-the-four-basic-forces-experienced-by-an-airplane&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/post/airplane/featured_hu6b2d4c0d1c8c130b9ed638ecabb5c823_4058_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpeg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;350&#34; height=&#34;144&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The four basic forces experienced by an airplane
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this was a group project, my friends and I decided to try our hands at designing a full-fledged airplane. It was quite different from what everyone else was doing, but we were determined to give it a go. The objectives we came up with for the project are summarized below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To design a full CAD model of an aircraft.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To fabricate the CAD model in parts, using 3-D printing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To move the control surfaces using servo motors and rotate the propeller using an electric motor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To make a deployable landing gear mechanism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We planned to manufacture each part individually using the 3D printer on campus. Considering the size of the parts and the 3D printer dimensions, the bigger parts like fuselage and wings had to be cut into 2-4 parts as per the requirements. Unfortunately, due to the dimensional restrictions of the 3D printer and a delay in procuring the materials, we were only able to fabricate a small prototype of the design, and not make the full-fledged scaled version we planned to make. Therefore, the objective of the movable control surfaces did not come to fruition either.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-the-3d-printed-prototype-we-were-able-to-fabricate&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/post/airplane/project_huc84e63f6dc77192f086a5c0ce1be1001_125664_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;400&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The 3D printed prototype we were able to fabricate
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This experience taught us a valuable lesson: translating an idea to a finished product takes a lot of effort, and there will be obstacles that we might not anticipate in the way. Since then, I have taken up various other electives and projects that have convinced me of my desire for pursuing higher studies and shaped my research acumen, but I certainly hope that I will get a chance to work on airplanes in the future, and maybe even build a functional one someday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aerodynamic Study of the flow field around the Tail Rotor and Fuselage of a Rotorcraft.</title>
      <link>https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 23:58:37 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project was the focus of my undergraduate thesis at the Rotorcraft Aerodynamic Laboratory at Politecnico di Milano, under the guidance of Prof. Luigi Vigevano, Associate Professor at the Department of Aerospace Engineering. In this thesis, the aerodynamic study of the flow field around the tail rotor and fuselage of a rotorcraft is conducted by generating a high-resolution grid using ANSYS ICEM. Subsequent simulations are carried out on the in-house CFD solver, ROSITA, using the Navier-Stokes governing equation combined with the Spallart-Allmaras Turbulence Model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bintroductionb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Introduction&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aerodynamics has always been at the cutting edge with respect to the development of aircraft and rotorcraft. With the development of computational methods and the resources to put them to use, aerodynamics has grown into something bigger and better. With today’s technology and tools, it is possible to analyze the flow past a stationary wing or a moving rotor and improve the design according to the requirements accordingly. Consequently, a lot of research has focused on this sector of the aerospace industry. With rotorcraft being more inherently complex aeromechanical vehicles, understanding the development of the flow field around them has lagged behind the traditional fixed-wing planes. Studying how the flow interacts and the noise it generates is garnering more attention as people are looking to increase the efficiency of future machines in terms of performance, as well as the generated sound. Therefore, understanding noise generation and its relation to the aerodynamics of rotorcraft is of the utmost importance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bcontext-of-the-present-workb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Context of the present work&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scientific work undertaken during this project is in the context of the work done by the European Action Group AG 24, ‘Helicopter Fuselage Scattering Effects for Exterior/Interior Noise Reduction’ in the Group for Aeronautical Research and Technology in Europe (GARTEUR). The objectives of this AG are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To develop and validate numerical prediction methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To generate a unique noise scattering database through wind tunnel tests using generic configurations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bobjectivesb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Objectives&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The objectives of my thesis were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Grid generation around the tail rotor and the fuselage used by the Group for Aeronautical Research and Technology in Europe (GARTEUR) for the study of scattering by the helicopter fuselage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Usage of the in-house solver, Rotorcraft Solver Italy (ROSITA), to run aerodynamic simulations on the isolated tail rotor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understanding the basics of aeroacoustics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simulating the Rotor plus Fuselage Configuration on ROSITA.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;ban-insight-into-noiseb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;An insight into Noise&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noise can be generated from rotorcraft from a variety of sources, out of which the rotor, the engine, and the transmission, are the major sources. In the previous two decades, noise reduction has received industrial attention due to certification rules becoming more stringent. Due to industrial involvement, the development of prediction codes has taken a turn for the better. To meet the needs of the industry, the research into noise reduction has taken off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noise is broadly classified into three categories, as shown in Figure 1:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;loading and broadband noise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blade-vortex noise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;thickness and high-speed impulsive noise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-1-different-kinds-of-noise-generated-by-a-helicopter-rotor&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/Fig.1_hu0c2932c643e9621c1149e8bdfdc1fa74_78611_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;600&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 1: Different kinds of noise generated by a Helicopter Rotor.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A helicopter rotor is essentially an unsteady mechanism due to the velocity difference between the advancing and retreating sides. As shown in Figure 2, this creates different kinds of impacts and wakes, leading to noise generation.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-2-a-schematic-of-the-aeromechanical-environment-of-a-helicopter-rotor&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/featured_hufae70a7c83ace065abfe7f91d4a16909_114735_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;674&#34; height=&#34;407&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 2: A schematic of the aeromechanical environment of a helicopter rotor.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prediction codes are used to simulate the noise generated by helicopters and are divided into the following two categories:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Computational Aeroacoustics Approach (CAA)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The approach based on Integral formulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While CAA permits a combined aerodynamic and aeroacoustic study, it is very computationally intensive, since it is based on the classical field methods. On the other hand, Integral methods have a pre-requisite of the aerodynamic knowledge around the rotor but are more suitable for obtaining aeroacoustic data at any point in the given field. It is in the development of such integral methods that the current research trend has its focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bgeometry-and-meshingb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Geometry and meshing&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The geometry used by AG24 is that of a simple fuselage, with a tail boom and a tail rotor. Since the focus of this project was only on the tail rotor, only the relevant parts were extracted, as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-3-blade-and-hub-assembly-with-part-of-the-drive-shaft&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/Fig.3_hu5be18ae7203f080ede98b2293bd41ce7_29327_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;400&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 3: Blade and Hub assembly, with part of the drive shaft
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For simplifying the simulation process, the hub and the drive shaft of the assembly are neglected during calculations, and the resultant geometry is depicted below:&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-4-only-the-blades&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/Fig.4_hu2ef0ed3b2f81acd20a1b5dffaafac1c7_6959_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;400&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 4: Only the Blades
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A high-resolution grid around the rotor is required for the computation of the aerodynamics around the specified geometry for achieving a mesh independent simulation. During the solving process, the mesh should also be able to tag onto another background mesh if necessary. Due to the flexibility it offers during meshing and the variety of options it provides for meshing complex and faceted geometries, ANSYS ICEM has been used as the meshing software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bsimulation-setupb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Simulation setup&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ROtorcraft Software ITAly (ROSITA), version V 4.63, is the in-house solver used for simulations during this thesis. Its core element is a multi-block-structured steady, or unsteady solver with a second-order discretization scheme that supports overset grids. It supports the usage of the Chimera method, also known as the overset mesh technique, for meshing the domain. The overset method has multiple meshes with different geometrical complexities and tag them to a single overarching mesh. In this scenario, the surface mesh is tagged to the background mesh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The methodology to be followed for running the simulation is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting up parameters like the Governing Equations, Turbulence model, and time step in the configuration file, ROSITA.cfg.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assigning the number of processors required for computation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Executing the code and running the post-processor after completion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ROSITA offers a variety of options for the solution: Solving the Euler equations, solving the Navier-Stokes equations without any turbulence model, and solving the RANS equations with a Spallart-Allmaras (S-A) turbulence model. To make a comparative study, the Blade Rotor simulation was run with two different setups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navier-Stokes equation without turbulence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navier-Stokes equation with Spallart-Allmaras turbulence model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bresult-extraction-on-tecplotb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Result extraction on Tecplot&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tecplot is a data visualization and post-processing software that is suitable for working with raw simulation data. Since the ROSITA post-processor outputs files in a Tecplot format, it is the natural choice for analyzing the results of the simulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distribution of pressure over the blade&amp;rsquo;s surface is an interesting phenomenon that calls to be investigated. It is also important from an aeroacoustic point of view since many noise propagation codes, and studies use the pressure field in their calculations. Therefore, obtaining a proper pressure distribution is essential, and a comparison to see which model yields the better results is made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ROSITA Solver generates two surface files in the .plt format, with data for each of the two blades. Combining the two files in Tecplot, we get the following image:&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-5-surface-pressure-contours-on-both-blades&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/polimi-thesis/Fig.5_hubed5b54afa66e2327a57c91e6472468d_17528_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;500&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 5: Surface pressure contours on both blades
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pressure contours are nearly symmetrical in the opposite direction and consistent with what is expected of a rotating blade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The behavior of the Mach Number contours provides proper insight into the aerodynamics of the flow field surrounding the rotor blade. Unlike pressure, it is not directly useful from an aeroacoustic point of view, but the implications in Aerodynamics are useful enough to study it in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bconclusionb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conclusion&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flow development around the tail rotor of the helicopter is mostly as expected, with a separation observed at the leading edge and a region of recirculation observed as the distance from the hub increases along the span of the blade. The observations made from the results can be summarized as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The oscillation in the solution is much lesser in the Turbulence Model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With an increase in y, the distance span-wise from the hub, the Mach Number as well as the flow separation increase, as expected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The difference in plots between the two cases is tangible, as the separation region is better defined with the turbulence model. This is because the S-A model specializes in solving boundary layers and adverse pressure gradients.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flow simulation of supercritical Carbon Dioxide through a channel</title>
      <link>https://atsis98.github.io/project/kharagpur/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Aug 2020 16:04:43 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://atsis98.github.io/project/kharagpur/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project was the focus of my research-oriented summer internship under Dr. Sourav Mitra, Assistant Professor at the Indian Institute of Technology, Kharagpur. It focused on simulating the flow of supercritical Carbon Dioxide (CO2) through a small channel, studying the velocity and temperature profiles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bintroductionb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Introduction&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the modern era of industrialization, many processes require the usage of solvents for different applications pertaining to the particular industry. For example, solvents are routinely used as paint removers, lacquers, adhesives, cleaning materials, etc. Different industries use different kinds of solvents for their applications, and with an increase in health awareness, the food industry is looking to move away from classic solvents. Due to this, supercritical Carbon Dioxide is finding favor in the coffee manufacturing industry, as a decaffeinating solvent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also gaining momentum in other industrial aspects, as a working fluid due to its relative stability, and as a component in power generation. Due to these advances and the growing use of Supercritical CO2, it is vital to study this fluid&amp;rsquo;s characteristics and behavior for innovative future applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bwhat-is-a-supercritical-fluidb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;What is a supercritical fluid?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A supercritical fluid is any fluid at a temperature and pressure above its critical point, where distinct liquid and gas phases do not exist. Applying temperature and pressure above the critical point of a substance pushes that substance into the supercritical phase. The properties of this fluid can be adjusted by going further into the supercritical region. This is achieved by increasing the temperature or pressure.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-1-depiction-of-various-phases&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/kharagpur/featured_hu6a5ba817c1370bba59b9bd21c40945ab_7869_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;500&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 1: Depiction of various phases
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bsupercritical-carbon-dioxideb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Supercritical Carbon Dioxide&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under normal atmospheric conditions, CO2 behaves as a gas. However, if the temperature and the pressure are increased to beyond the parameters of its critical point, it starts behaving midway between a liquid and a gas. This is called the supercritical state of CO2, with the fluid having a density similar to that of a liquid while occupying a volume in the same way a gas does. The parameters for the critical point for CO2 are given below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Temperature: 304.25 K
Pressure: 7.39 MPa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bsimulation-setup-for-normal-co2b&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Simulation setup for normal CO2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To get familiarized with the behavior of CO2 in a flow channel, it was first simulated under normal conditions. The properties of CO2 were imported from NIST REFPROP, by writing a line of code in ANSYS Fluent to initialize the REFPROP database, and select the corresponding CO2 file to be imported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pipe length was set to be 0.1m, and the diameter as 0.005m. The boundary conditions are summarized below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inlet velocity = 0.5 m/s
Temperature of Fluid at inlet = 300 K
Wall Temperature = 273 K
Outlet: Outflow Condition
Walls: No-slip condition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The velocity and temperature profiles are plotted for the entire region, with analysis conducted on 9 sections across the length.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-2-velocity-profiles-at-each-of-the-9-slices&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/kharagpur/fig1_hu7c4308242bdac15171d0d224bea94f38_45979_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;500&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 2: Velocity profiles at each of the 9 slices
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we see that the velocity converges to parabolic throughout the course of the flow.&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-3-temperature-profiles-at-each-of-the-9-slices&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/kharagpur/fig2_hu95052270e72abb6f0f78e30d5963d6ec_47501_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;500&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 3: Temperature profiles at each of the 9 slices
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we see that the temperature profile converges to parabolic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the above data and analysis, we can conclude that flow of CO2 through a pipe develops, both hydrodynamically and thermally, after a certain point, as shown by the calculations. The next step is to simulate a similar case for supercritical flow, with the temperature and pressure being inputted accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bsimulation-setup-for-supercritical-co2b&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Simulation setup for supercritical CO2&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The setup remains the same, except for the temperature of the fluid at the inlet, which is changed to 304.25 K, the supercritical temperature of CO2. However, at the supercritical pressure and temperature, the simulation in Fluent did not behave as expected, even if the outlet boundary condition is changed. So far, the NIST Real gas tables have been linked with the Fluent console. Since the results were not satisfactory, a different approach was required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fundamental properties such as density and thermal conductivity were explicitly exported from REFPROP into MS-Excel, and their variations with temperature were plotted. Using the trend line feature of Excel, the approximate polynomials for the respective graphs were extracted, as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;






  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-figure-4-physical-properties-as-plotted-in-excel&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;https://atsis98.github.io/project/kharagpur/fig3_hudb3164edf7eb247aaf7b06ff45def06f_70741_2000x2000_fit_lanczos_2.png&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;750&#34; height=&#34;750&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Figure 4: Physical properties as plotted in Excel
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These polynomials are then inputted into Fluent as a new material, corresponding to CO2. When the User-Defined Function (UDF) was discarded, and the polynomials were inputted with the right units, there were no further errors in the initialization phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simulation was run at an inlet velocity of 1m/s, keeping all the other boundary conditions the same. The velocity contour, however, was almost uniform, even though the flow was laminar. The same simulation was run at 0.01 m/s, and the velocity contour behaved as expected. Seeing this anomaly, the domain length was changed to 1m to see if there were any discernable changes in a larger flow domain. The velocity and temperature profiles are quite different, while the specific heat contours show a slight variation, and the pressure contours behave almost the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bconclusionb&#34;&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conclusion&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the variable material properties of supercritical carbon dioxide have successfully been imported into Fluent, utilizing the NIST provided REFPROP software. The polynomials generated through MS Excel have proved to be durable. The resulting velocity and temperature contours are deviant from the expected results and need to be probed into. Once this issue is resolved, the simulation can then be moved to a microchannel, with additional parameters like surface tension coming into play.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A day in the life of a NALCO intern</title>
      <link>https://atsis98.github.io/post/ps1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 16:00:51 +0530</pubDate>
      <guid>https://atsis98.github.io/post/ps1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The article chronicles a typical day during my internship at the National Aluminium Company, Mines and Refinery Complex, at Damanjodi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alarm rings. I reach to my side and turn it off. Somewhere, my subconscious self tells me to get up and wash those clothes lying in my bag, but my sleepy mind tunes it out and decides to wait for the next alarm by sleeping again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7:10 am – the dutiful alarm rings once again. I open my eyes, turn it off again, not realizing that it is the last of the three alarms I set. My eyes close, and when they open again, a sudden panic sets in on me, I turn to look at my phone and see that it’s 7:35. I jolt awake and drop my phone in the process. Perfect. I just hope it’s not broken. The moment of trepidation passes as I see that it’s safe. I scramble into the bathroom to brush and take a bath.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me give you a little context as to why waking up at 7:35 is a disaster. My PS station is at the National Aluminium Company, Refinery and Mines Complex, Damanjodi. The working hours are 8 to 5, six days a week, and the 17 of us from all three campuses of BITS are trainees for the summer.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-the-entrance-to-the-nalco-plant&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;featured.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;600&#34; height=&#34;600&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The entrance to the NALCO Plant
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me tell you a little bit about the plant as well. Its primary purpose is to obtain alumina from the raw Bauxite so that it can be sent to the other plant in Angul to obtain aluminium. So, the entire refinery uses various techniques to produce alumina through a process called Bayer’s Process.&lt;/p&gt;
















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-a-view-of-the-steam-and-power-plant&#34;&gt;



  &lt;img data-src=&#34;plant.jpg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;375&#34;&gt;



  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    A view of the Steam and Power Plant
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, coming back to today, I rushed to get ready by 8. Got there by 8:10, hurriedly woke my roommates and waited for them to get ready as well. By the time we got ready, called an auto and reached the gate, it was 9:20. After a little drama at the gate for being late, we went to have breakfast at the canteen and then went to our respective departments. I had been allotted the Steam and Power Plant (SPP), which served the double purpose of generating steam to be used in the process and generating electricity as a by-product. I went to meet my mentor, and he sat me down and explained how a boiler works. Since I have only completed my second year, I have limited knowledge of things that concern the plant, and whatever I’ve been learning here is almost entirely new.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I listened to him with a combination of fascination and boredom, and when he had finished with the basic outline, he sent me to the boiler control room to visit the actual thing. A site engineer showed me around the place, explaining how things worked while showing me the different components and connections that worked perfectly in harmony to produce the desired results. I will not go into the technical details, partly because I don’t know them completely, but mostly because I wouldn’t want you getting bored with them.
After the site visit, I went back to my mentor’s office. My days till now had mostly consisted of him teaching me things that I would learn in my third year, and their practical applications. I soon got used to the routine, and have begun to learn quite a few things, which I’m sure will help me in my studies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went back around 11:30, and the two of us discussed how water was converted to steam and then superheated, through the boiler and its accessories. Although it sounds like a simple process, there is more to it than meets the eye. Every little detail has to be taken care of; every parameter scrutinized if the entire apparatus has to function as per requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He told me to study about boiler auxiliaries and mountings. Usually, he asks me to come back in the afternoon for another site visit, but today was different. He told me that without at least a basic knowledge of what’s going on in the system, a site visit would not be beneficial. He therefore let me go back to the hostel at 1, telling me to come prepared tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I walked the 3 kilometres to the main gate, elated at the half-day and got into an auto that took me back to my hostel. Another day gone, where I learnt a little, experienced a new marvel of engineering, satisfied a little bit of my curiosity, and got an unexpected let off as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good day indeed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
